<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The loue of VVales to their soueraigne prince expressed in a true relation of the solemnity held at Ludlow in the countie of Salop, vpon the fourth of Nouember last past. Anno Domini. 1616. Being the day of the creation of the high and mighty Charles, Prince of Wales, and Earle of Chester, in his Maiesties palace of White-Hall.</title>
            <author>Powel, Daniel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09895</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20159</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115024</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850244</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850244</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15431</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09895)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15431)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1329:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The loue of VVales to their soueraigne prince expressed in a true relation of the solemnity held at Ludlow in the countie of Salop, vpon the fourth of Nouember last past. Anno Domini. 1616. Being the day of the creation of the high and mighty Charles, Prince of Wales, and Earle of Chester, in his Maiesties palace of White-Hall.</title>
                  <author>Powel, Daniel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Daniel Powel.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ D² .</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
               <term>Ludlow (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15431:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15431:1"/>
            <p>THE LOVE OF VVALES to their ſoueraigne Prince, <hi>Expreſſed</hi> In a true Relation of the ſolemnity <hi>held at</hi> Ludlow <hi>in the Countie of Salop,</hi> vpon the fourth of Nouember laſt paſt. <hi>Anno Domini.</hi> 1616.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Being the day of the Creation of the</hi> high and mighty CHARLES, Prince of WALES, and Earle of CHESTER, <hi>in his Maieſties Palace of</hi> White-Hall.</p>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by</hi> Nicholas Okes, 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15431:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15431:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the high and mightie Prince <hi>CHARLES, Prince of</hi> Wales, Duke of <hi>Cornewall</hi> and <hi>Yorke,</hi> and Earle <hi>of</hi> Cheſter, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Illuſtrious and Peereleſſe Prince,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth in the Sunne riſing, how in diſplaying his bright Beames, hee diſpells all miſtie vapours, and comforts, by the vigorous influence thereof, the feeble ſences of inferior bodies: the ſame might eaſily haue bin diſcerned in the faces of all his Maieſties ſubiects (who formerly drouping through the Fates deſtinie) are at laſt cheered and reuiued by the happy <hi>Riſe</hi> of your <hi>Highnes</hi> into the <hi>Princely</hi> throne of <hi>Wales,</hi> where you were no ſooner enthronized by Gods graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous prouidence, by lawfull authoritie, and by the loue
<pb facs="tcp:15431:3"/>of all his Maieſties liege people (who are the Princes principall Supporters) but it was a wonder to ſee of a ſudden, what a ſweet ſpring, what a happie change, what a powerfull renouation was wrought in the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſpirits of his Maieſties ſayd ſubiects, who daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced for ioy, filled the Aire with ſhouts and acclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in all quarters, but ſpecially in your proper Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian of <hi>Ludlow,</hi> the beautifull ſeate of his Maieſties chiefe Caſtle and Counſell of <hi>Wales,</hi> where my ſelfe (being not altogether an idle Actor, nor vnwilling Spectator) was ſo rauiſhed with the fullneſſe of ioy, which I ſaw in the hearts of the people, as I wiſhed my ſelfe then to bee transformed into the ſhape of the ſweete Nightingale, which was counted <hi>Vox prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereà nihil,</hi> that with Fames golden wings I might eccho out to the eares of all men, the loyall affection of the <hi>Brittiſh Nation</hi> to their royall <hi>Prince,</hi> and the <hi>royall fauours</hi> of their <hi>gracious Prince</hi> intended to them, whoſe very Name cauſed ſuch a ſurpluſage of mirth and admiration, as my Penne is not able to decipher the halfe of the reioycing which they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, nor were they any way able with all their indeuors, to teſtifie the full meaſure of Gladnes which their hearts conceiued: If then in the divulging of this plaine Narration, I eclipſe much of the glorious ſubſtance of the Shew, I hope your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding my loyall intention, will be induced to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don my daring preſumption. And what is now the period of all our Petitions, but that Heauen may adde conſtancie to the felicitie of your <hi>Triumph,</hi> and then
<pb facs="tcp:15431:3"/>we doubt not that our <hi>Ioyes</hi> ſhall euer waxe olde, but whiles your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> continues to accept of the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Title of <hi>Prince of Wales,</hi> his Maieſties people will ſtill haue new matter of reioycing in your graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Gouernment and powerfull protection: Thus in moſt lowly manner vpon my knee, crauing pardon for this my preſumption, hoping your <hi>Excellencie</hi> will not diſcuſſe <hi>Nec quis, nec quid, ſed quo animo,</hi> neyther the meaneneſſe of my ſelfe, nor the ſmallneſſe of the matter, but onely the minde and heart of your poore <hi>Vaſſall,</hi> I reſt praying for all bleſsings external, internall, and eternall to your <hi>Highneſſe.</hi> 
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From <hi>Ludlow</hi> 
                  <date>this laſt of Nouember <hi>1616.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Highneſſe deuoted in all obſeruance</hi> Daniel Powel.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15431:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which <hi>Virgill</hi> writeth of <hi>Aſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> his following his Father <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas,</hi> I muſt apply at this time to my ſelfe;</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">ſequitur<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> patrem, haud paſsibus ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis.</q>
            <p>My naturall Father ſo loued his natiue Country, that (amongſt other Writings) he wrote a Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle of <hi>Wales;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doctor <hi>Powels</hi> Chronicle.</note> and I, howbeit not able to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him in like maturitie and perfection, yet ſtriuing to follow him in the like matter and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, haue aduentured to relate the great cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe and exceeding forwardneſſe, which was in my Country-men, and all in theſe parts, vpon the day of his <hi>Highneſſe</hi> Creation <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Wales.</hi> And how euer the carping <hi>Critickes</hi> may calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niate my honeſt indeuours, yet I am ſure they can neuer obliterate the memory of that daies mirth, which ſtill remaines <hi>niueo ſignanda lapillo,</hi> ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred
<pb facs="tcp:15431:4"/>in the hearts of the people; <hi>Vt nulla vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam aetas, nulla aetatis vetuſtas, nulla vetuſtatis an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitas illam aboleuerit.</hi> Which if thou take in good part, it is all I deſire; if thou doe not, it is enough that I teſtifie my humble duetie vnto my <hi>Prince</hi> for his content, and my loue to my Country-men for their commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, and ſo I leaue thee.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_participants">
            <pb facs="tcp:15431:5"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>¶ <hi>Apud</hi> Ludlow <date>
                     <hi>quarto die</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uembris, Anno Domini 1616. <hi>Anno<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Regni Regis</hi> IACOBI <hi>nunc, &amp;c.</hi> Angliae, Franciae, &amp; Hyberniae, &amp;c. <hi>Quartodecimo: Et Scociae</hi> Quinquageſimo.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <list>
               <head>The names of ſuch of the Counſell there, as then were preſent.</head>
               <item>Sir <hi>THOMAS CHAMBERLAINE</hi> Knight, Sergeant at Law, chiefe Iuſtice of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and of his Maieſties Counſell in the Marches of <hi>Wales.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>THOMAS CORNEVVAILE</hi> Knight, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of <hi>Burford,</hi> one of the Gentlemen of his Maieſties priuie Chamber, high Sheriffe of the County of <hi>Salop,</hi> one other of his Maieſties ſaid Counſell there.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>THOMAS HARLEY</hi> Eſquier, one other of his Maieſties ſaid Counſell there.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:15431:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE LO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E OF</hi> VVALES to their ſoueraigne <hi>Prince.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Is Maieſties ſaid Counſell in the Dominion and Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palitie of <hi>Wales,</hi> and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the ſame (beeing at <hi>Ludlow,</hi> where his Highneſſe chiefe Seate and Caſtle for the ſaid Principalitie, now is, and of a long time hath beene) for a Remembrance to all ſucceeding A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, haue (by the appoyntment and direction of the right honourable <hi>Raph</hi> Lord <hi>Eure,</hi> Lord Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of the ſaid Counſell beeing then abſent) commaunded, that the ſaid day, in the yeare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, being Monday the firſt day of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Terme, holden before the ſaid Counſell (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:15431:6"/>the very day, whereon the moſt renowned, high, and mightie Prince CHARLES Prince of Great <hi>Britaine,</hi> &amp;c. was at his Maieſties Pallace of <hi>White-Hall</hi> created <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Wales,</hi> and <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Cheſter</hi>) ſhould be ſolemnized.</p>
            <p>For which purpoſe, the ſaid <hi>Iuſtice</hi> tooke ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall care, as the ſhortnes of the time would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, being newly come from <hi>London,</hi> where hee left ſir <hi>Henry Touneſhend,</hi> and ſir <hi>Francis Eure</hi> Knights, with <hi>Nicholas Ouerbury</hi> Eſquier, three of the learned Counſell Reſident for the ſaide Principalitie and Marches thereof, at that time attending his Maieſties ſpeciall ſeruice at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don:</hi>) and cauſed to repaire, and aſſemble at the ſaid Caſtle of <hi>Ludlow,</hi> the forenamed ſir <hi>Thomas Cornewaile</hi> high Sherife of the ſayd County, with his Staffe of Office, and the ſaid <hi>Thomas Harley</hi> Eſquier (being two of his Counſell there as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd) together with ſir <hi>Robert Harley</hi> Knight of the Bath, ſir <hi>Francis Cornwaile</hi> Knight, <hi>Marma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke Lloyd</hi> Eſquier, his Maieſties Atturney there, <hi>Thomas Powell</hi> Eſquier his Highneſſe Sollicitor, attending the ſayd Counſell, <hi>Iohn Delabere</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of Phyſicke, <hi>William Fox, William Vaughan, Gruffith Lloyd</hi> Eſquiers, and many other worthy Gentlemen and perſons of good account of the Counties of <hi>Salop, Hereford, Denbigh, Mountgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gomery, Caeruaruon, Merioneth,</hi> and other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries adioyning, to the number of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand perſons.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15431:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The true manner of which Solemnization was as followeth:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>FIrſt, the ſaid <hi>Iuſtice</hi> commanded that our ſaid Prince his Armes, with his Name, and Stile there-vnder in Characters fairely ſubſcribed, ſhould be ſet vp and publiſhed, as well vnder the Pulpit in the church of Saint <hi>Laurence</hi> in <hi>Ludlow,</hi> and in his Maieſties Chappel within the ſaid Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, and in the Court-houſe of the Principalitie there, as alſo vpon the gates of the ſaid Towne, and high Croſſe there, and likewiſe vppon the principall Poſts and Pillars ſtanding in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket place within the ſaid Towne of <hi>Ludlow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The tenour of which Stile and Subſcription here inſueth.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="royal_style">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Quarto Nouembris. Anno Dom. 1616.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He right high, Mighty and excellent Prince</hi> Charles, <hi>Prince of great</hi> Britaine <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>Duke of</hi> Cornewall, Yorke <hi>and of</hi> Albany, <hi>Marqueſſe of</hi> Ormont, <hi>Earle of</hi> Roſſe, <hi>Baron of</hi> Armanoch, <hi>of the moſt noble or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:15431:7"/>of the Garter, Knight, Second Sonne by Birth, and now the only and firſt begotten ſonne of the moſt puiſſant and potent</hi> Iames <hi>by the grace of God, of</hi> England, Scotland France <hi>and</hi> Ireland <hi>King, is this day at</hi> Lud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>by vs of the Counſell ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed within the ſaid Principalitie of</hi> Wales.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Afterwards, about nine of the Clocke in the fore-noone of the ſaid fourth of Nouember, <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Gregory,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Blaſhfield</hi> Eſquiers, Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifes of the ſaid Towne of <hi>Ludlow,</hi> accompanied with the Magiſtrates their Brethren, and all the chiefe Burgeſſes of the ſaid Towne, very richly clad and apparrelled, attended by their Officers with their Maces before them, and all the Quire of the Church there, ſinging of Hymnes and Pſalmes of thankeſgiuing and praiſe for our ſayd Prince, bringing with them ſixe yong Youths, being Schollers of the Kings free Schoole of the ſaid Towne, well and richly decked and adorned,
<pb facs="tcp:15431:7"/>who did beare in their hands ſeuerall Penons and Bannerolls of the Armes and Atchiuements of our ſaid Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> that is to ſay:</p>
            <p>The formoſt Scholler bore in his hand the Armes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond carried the Armes of the <hi>Brittaines</hi> and <hi>Saxons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third, <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth, <hi>Northwales</hi> and <hi>Southwales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fift, <hi>Cornewall</hi> and <hi>Cheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſixt and the laſt, carried the Armes of <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> with the Plume of feathers and the Prince his Name;</p>
            <p>Hauing before them the Towne Waites and other lowd Inſtruments of Muſicke, and before the muſicke marched a long the number of two hundred ſouldiers being well appointed and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with Halberds, Pikes, Corſlets, Muskets, and Caliuers, vnder the conduct and leading of <hi>Leonard Lloyd</hi> there then Captaine (who in good order had his Lieutenants, and Sergeants braue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly arrayed, hauing foure Drums, and two Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets ſounding before them, beſides Fifes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther winde Inſtruments, who all of them thus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted, came vp to the Caſtle to attend and bring the ſaid <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and <hi>Counſell</hi> to the Church:</p>
            <p>And hauing repayred to the Caſtle Greene there, and meeting Maiſter <hi>Iuſtice</hi> in his Scarlet Robes, with the reſt of the Counſell before na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in decent maner, vpon the Caſtle bridge, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied
<pb facs="tcp:15431:8"/>with all the worſhipfull Counſellors of Law, Atturneis and Clarks belonging to that Court, with ſundry Eſquiers and Gentlemen, hauing before them <hi>Richard Iones</hi> Eſquier, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant at Armes, carrying his Maieſties Mace, <hi>William Gooderick</hi> Eſquier, gentleman Porter, <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Collins,</hi> one of the Vſhers of his Maieſties Chamber, and the two meſſengers of the Court, <hi>viz. Piers Gruffith,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Pingle</hi> gentlemen, in rich coates; <hi>Francis Trollop</hi> gentleman, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall of the ſaid Court, <hi>Thomas Steuens</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Yeoman of the Kings Wardrobe there, <hi>Gruffith Iones</hi> Conſtable of the Caſtle, together with all the chiefe Officers of the ſaid Caſtle (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all of them very richly apparrelled, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing another company of Waits and good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorts of Muſicke, as Cornets, Sagbuts, and other winde Inſtruments, playing and ſounding all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the way before them) a great Volley of ſhot was diſcharged by the ſaid Muskettiers and Cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, which ſo pierced the Ayre with the great noyſe of Drummes, and ſound of Trumpets, Fifes, Flutes, and other Inſtruments, as the like in theſe parts hath not beene ſeene, to the great admiration, and much reioycing of all the Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators.</p>
            <p>And thereupon marſhalling themſelues in good array, they all went through the Towne ſtreets, to the Church, ſinging and reioycing all the way they went, where was another Volley of ſhotte diſcharged.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15431:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>After Prayers ſaid, and Pſalmes ſung, one <hi>M. Thomas Pierſon,</hi> a graue reuerend diuine and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Preacher, made a very learned Sermon of an houre and halfe long, vpon the firſt verſe of the 72. Pſalme, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Giue the King thy Iudgements, O God, and thy Righteouſneſſe to the Kings ſonne.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Which Sermon being ended, and Pſalmes ſung by the Singing-men and Quiriſters, to and with the great Organs there, all the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany returned.</p>
            <p>And as they iſſued out of the Church and Church-yard into the Market place, there was a new Scaffolde purpoſly erected neare vnto the high Croſſe (with a great Bonefire not farre di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant) vpon which Scaffolde the ſaid Schollers with their Penons or Banerols of Armes in their hands, as aforeſaid, aſcended; and as the ſaid <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> and Counſell paſſed by, <hi>alternatim</hi> vttered, and pronounced theſe ſeuerall Speeches follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="lat" type="speech">
               <body>
                  <l>
                     <hi>CAmbria</hi> tolle caput nuper perpeſſa dolores</l>
                  <l>Gaudia nunc animo conduplicata tuo.</l>
                  <l>Auſpicijs laetis <hi>Princeps</hi> hac luce creatur,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Carolus:</hi> ô totus Gratia, totus Amor!</l>
                  <l>Splendida progenies coelo delapſa ſupremo</l>
                  <l>Deliciae noſtri dimidium<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Iouis!</l>
                  <l>Pluribus obſequijs nos hac de gente tenemur</l>
                  <l>ô <hi>Princeps</hi> laudes amplificare tuas.</l>
                  <l>Pluribus officijs nos <hi>hac de ſede loco<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15431:9"/>
                  <l>Debemus titulos concelebrare tuos.</l>
                  <l>Ecce tua ipſius proprio tibi iure dicata</l>
                  <l>Symbola: iudicibus conueneranda Dijs</l>
                  <l>Pluma triplex rutilâ pulchre deuincta coronâ</l>
                  <l>Orbis inexhauſtas flammeus ambit eas</l>
                  <l>Illa feras, pardoſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> truces, aquilaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fugaces</l>
                  <l>Exuperant titulis nobilitata ſuis.</l>
                  <l>Scilicet in coelum ſuper aetheris ardua Sanctos</l>
                  <l>Virtutum ſtudijs penna volare notat.</l>
                  <l>Vox diuina ſubeſt coeleſti pectore digna</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Ych Dyn,</note>Sub Iouis Imperijs * <hi>Seruio</hi> non alijs.</l>
                  <l>Nemo meis dignus niſi qui ſit Summus in orbe</l>
                  <l>Officijs: Sors eſt libera nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> mea.</l>
                  <l>Sic antiqua docent nos Vatum oracula recte</l>
                  <l>(Sors eſt à primâ Sorte ſecunda mea.)</l>
                  <l>Clara coronatae nos hic Inſignia plumae</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Principis</hi> armigeri ſcutiferi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> damus.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vir venerandè tibi; quae (te cuſtode) repoſta</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Principis <hi>hinc noſtri nomen in aſtra ferant.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <byline>Dixit IOHANNES COTTON.</byline>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="lat" type="speech">
               <body>
                  <l>POndera magna (licet pueri) geſtamus; HOnoris</l>
                  <l>Plena; ſed Herculeis viribus aequa ſatis</l>
                  <l>Atlantiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Humeris: de Gentibus vndi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> noſtris</l>
                  <l>Debetur titulis Imperialis honos.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Anglia</hi> prima ſuos clariſsima ſigna Leones</l>
                  <l>Geſtat: cognatos <hi>Scotia</hi> geſtat eos</l>
                  <l>Inde perantiquo ſplendentes lumine Gentes</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Brito</hi> Leone nitet: <hi>Saxo</hi> crucem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> gerit.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15431:9"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gallia</hi> ſuccedit, cui iuncta <hi>Hybernica</hi> tellus</l>
                  <l>Portans dulciſonae Lilia nexa Lyrae.</l>
                  <l>Hinc diuiſa<note n="*" place="margin">Ordouices &amp; Silures. <hi>Northwales &amp; Southwales.</hi>
                     </note> duas in partes <hi>Cambria:</hi> Sunt<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </l>
                  <l>Signa Leone rapax cum gradiente Leo.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ceſtria</hi> geſtit ouans &amp; ouans <hi>Cornubia</hi> quinto</l>
                  <l>Oſtentans titulos amplificanſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſuos</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eboraco</hi> tandem <hi>Lancaſtria</hi> iungitur: illis</l>
                  <l>Candida purpureae ſic roſa iuncta roſae.</l>
                  <l>Singula pulchra ſatis licet ingens pondus Honoris</l>
                  <l>Sola tenent: Ducibus nobilitata ſuis</l>
                  <l>Vnde paterna fluit materna<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Gentis origo</l>
                  <l>Regibus innumeris quae numeretur auis</l>
                  <l>At ſplendoris habent immenſum corpore in vno</l>
                  <l>Crux, Roſa, Spica, Globi, Lilia, Plectra, Leo.</l>
                  <l>Vis vnita valet: virtus coniuncta niteſcit</l>
                  <l>Clarior: Haec noſtri <hi>Principis</hi> arma docent</l>
                  <l>Significant<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſuis. Quae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> haec digniſsima ſacris</l>
                  <l>Arcanis, (Vatum ni minuenda fides)</l>
                  <l>Diuinos mores, coeleſtia pectora, Mentes</l>
                  <l>Pluſquam mortales Regibus eſſe pijs.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hos fidei curae<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> tuae mandamus Honores</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O princeps noſtri lux<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> decuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Fori.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <byline>Dixit THO: FISHER.</byline>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="lat" type="speech">
               <body>
                  <l>QVid Phaebaea canit vel iactat nomina Delos?</l>
                  <l>Creta quid omnipotens nomen Iouiale recenſet?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Principis</hi> haec noſtri ſuperabit nomina nomen</l>
                  <l>Clara per immenſum fundens miracula mundum?</l>
                  <l>Illum pro cunctis ſua <hi>Cambria</hi> praedicet vnum</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15431:10"/>
                  <l>Vnum prae cunctis vaga fama recenſeat illum,</l>
                  <l>Spargat &amp; <hi>Argolicas</hi> tua nomina clara per vrbes</l>
                  <l>Vrbes <hi>Italiae</hi> noſcant tua nomina tanta</l>
                  <l>Tanta per <hi>Aſſyrios</hi> volitent tua nomina muros</l>
                  <l>Muros <hi>Barbariae</hi> colluſtrent nomina ſacra</l>
                  <l>Sacra vel extremae captant tua nomina Gentes</l>
                  <l>Gentes condiſcant &amp; tradant Poſteritati,</l>
                  <l>Poſteritas tanto gaudebit nomine laeta</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Carole</hi> gentis honos noſtrae, Lux altera Mundi.</l>
                  <byline>Dixit SIMON COTTON.</byline>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="lat" type="speech">
               <body>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Haec dies nobis niueo lapillo</l>
                     <l>Haec dies feſto numeranda ramo</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Carolus Princeps</hi> pius hac nitenti Luce creatur.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Principi</hi> noſtro meritos honores</l>
                     <l>Maximos illi meritoſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> amores</l>
                     <l>Demus: &amp; quartae memores Nouembris Simus in aeuum.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Bellicus artes amet &amp; Trophaea</l>
                     <l>Candidus doctis faueat Camoenis</l>
                     <l>Victor educto gladio rebellem Terreat hoſtem.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Inclytus factis ſuper aſtra notis</l>
                     <l>Exprimat patrem, pietate matrem</l>
                     <l>Et Senex vitae numeret beatae Tempora longa.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <byline>Dixit EDOARDVS SAVNDERS.</byline>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb facs="tcp:15431:10"/>
            <p>All which were principally inuented and made by the painfull induſtrie of that iudicious and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious maiſter of Artes <hi>Humfrey Herbert</hi> chiefe Schoole-maiſter of his Maieſties free-Schoole there, vpon one dayes warning.</p>
            <p>As alſo theſe that follow, were then pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, being made by that worthy Alderman of <hi>Ludlow</hi> maiſter <hi>Richard Fiſher.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
               <body>
                  <l>That which the fullneſſe of our Ioy brings forth,</l>
                  <l>Although not equall to the cauſes worth;</l>
                  <l>That which our humble duetie moues vs to,</l>
                  <l>All that our meane Abilitie can do,</l>
                  <l>Vnto our deare Prince <hi>Charles</hi> we conſecrate,</l>
                  <l>His faire beginning to congratulate,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Charles</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Camdens</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines.</note> 
                     <hi>Valiant</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d<note n="b" place="margin">Verſtegans e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymolog.</note> 
                     <hi>All-Noble</hi> ſignifies,</l>
                  <l>And loe, theſe Emblemes well the ſame implies</l>
                  <l>The<note n="c" place="margin">Cardan. inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta ſuperare ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificat.</note> Oſtrich feathers, <hi>Fortitude</hi> expreſſe</l>
                  <l>The Kingly<note n="d" place="margin">Principem &amp; virum magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimum.</note> Lions intimate no leſſe:</l>
                  <l>The<note n="e" place="margin">Symbolu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianae proſeſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</note> Croſſe <hi>Religion,</hi> and theſe fragrant<note n="f" place="margin">Lilium &amp; ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſae, pulchritudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, gratiam, bonam famam, &amp; iuſta facta pollicentur.</note> flowers</l>
                  <l>The<note n="g" place="margin">Harmonia, ſapientiam diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam.</note> Slaſh, the<note n="h" place="margin">Vnitatem &amp; ſecuritatem.</note> Globes &amp;<note n="i" place="margin">Garbae, ſpicae deorum ſunt coronae, proſperitatem &amp; benignitatem ſignificant &amp; denotant. Cardan.</note> Crowne of heauenly powers,</l>
                  <l>Are Hieroglyphicks of <hi>Nobilitie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>High Birth, true Wiſedome, Iuſtice, Pietie.</l>
                  <l>Theſe we preſent vnto his ſacred Name,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe worth containes the Character of Fame.</l>
                  <byline>THOMAS GREGORIE.</byline>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb facs="tcp:15431:11"/>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
               <body>
                  <l>THrice bleſſed be the heauenly Prouidence,</l>
                  <l>That gau's a <hi>Prince</hi> of ſuch magnificence,</l>
                  <l>Who is the moſt illuſtrious flowring Bud</l>
                  <l>Of many famous Kingdomes royall Blud,</l>
                  <l>And our great <hi>Britaines</hi> hopefull ornament</l>
                  <l>Hee ſhall protect this happy<note n="*" place="margin">The Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the Marches.</note> Gouernment.</l>
                  <l>And proudeſt oppoſition learne to know,</l>
                  <l>The Dutie to our Soueraigne King we owe.</l>
                  <l>Now <hi>Ludlow</hi> maiſt thou hope (if Gods will bee)</l>
                  <l>Thy <hi>Princes</hi> ſacred perſon heere to ſee,</l>
                  <l>And ſtreame out all thy Ioyes to veiw his Face,</l>
                  <l>And ſome officious ſeruice do his Grace.</l>
                  <l>O proſper may he, and his glory more,</l>
                  <l>Then any <hi>Charles</hi> the World had e're before:</l>
                  <l>His future yeares exceeding ten times ten,</l>
                  <l>All thoſe that loue Prince <hi>Charles</hi> will ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <byline>WALTER ASTON.</byline>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>THe which Speeches being ended by the ſaid Schollers (who thereby for their gracious boldneſſe in the deliuerie thereof, got great ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe by the ſaid <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and all the Auditorie) and after another volley of ſhot diſcharged, they marched and paſſed by ſundry other great Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires, whereof one was by the Caſtle Gate, and another was within the vtter Court, or Greene of
<pb facs="tcp:15431:11"/>the ſaid Caſtle, and there marching, diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of ſhot, ſinging, playing on inſtruments and heartily reioycing, proceeded into the Court-houſe of the ſaid Principalitie, where the ſaid <hi>Iuſtice</hi> very grauely, in the preſence and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of all the whole Company there aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, deliuered theſe words following, or the like in effect, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>THis happy and glorious Day, the bright Sunne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhining glory of Great</hi> Britaine, <hi>being the firſt day of the Weeke, and the firſt day of our Terme, and the next day to the Lords owne Day, his holy Sabaoth: and the next day before our won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull day of our great deliuerance from the Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder-Treaſon, the Kings day:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The High and Mighty Prince</hi> Charles <hi>our firſt Prince of that Name, Prince of Great</hi> Britaine <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>Duke of</hi> Cornewall, Yorke, <hi>and</hi> Albany, <hi>Marques of</hi> Ormont, <hi>Earle of</hi> Roſſe, <hi>Baron of</hi> Armanoch, <hi>of the moſt Noble Order of the Garter, Knight: Second Sonne by Birth, and now the Onely, and Firſt Begotten Sonne of the moſt potent and puiſſant</hi> IAMES, <hi>by the Grace of God, of</hi> England, Scotland, France <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>King; is this day, at his</hi> Maieſties <hi>Palace of</hi> White-hall, <hi>created</hi> Prince <hi>of</hi> Wales <hi>and</hi> Earle <hi>of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>being the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Prince by Creation, in ſucceſsion of this his Noble Principalitie of</hi> Wales.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15431:12"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>This moſt excellent</hi> Prince <hi>thus ſtated and ſtiled, takes it for a high honour, and great dignitie vnto himſelfe to be created</hi> Prince <hi>of</hi> Wales; <hi>and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all we of this Principalitie and Iuriſdiction, are the rather bound to yeeld all honour, dutie and ſeruice to him who hath ſo much honoured vs, and all</hi> Wales.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And therefore let none ſcorne nor contemne the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and authoritie thereof, (his Highneſſe being graciouſly pleaſed to ſignifie his pleaſure to me and my ſaid Brethren of this Counſell) That he would protect and defend the ſame both by his Highneſſe himſelfe, and by his Princely meanes to the King his father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And as he is now our firſt</hi> Prince <hi>of that name, ſo I hope he ſhalbe as religious, victorious, and renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned within theſe his Maieſties Kingdoms and the Dominions thereof in future times, as thoſe of his Name haue bene in other Kingdomes in former A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges before him, to the great glory of great</hi> Britaine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore all our Prayers to God ſhalbe, that our ſaid</hi> Prince <hi>may be a continuall comfort and Honour to the King his father, our dread Soueraigne, during his raigne (which God long continue) and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to be the ſtaffe and ſtrength of vs and all Chriſtendome, for the protection and defence of the Church of God, his holy word and Goſpel, and that God will bleſſe Prince</hi> Charles <hi>our ſaid Prince of</hi> Wales, <hi>with all his bleſsings from Heauen, fit for ſo high and mighty a</hi> Prince <hi>as he is; as alſo with long life, royall iſſue, and happy dayes, for the
<pb facs="tcp:15431:12"/>good and welfare of this our Church and Common-wealth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And let this happy day of the</hi> Creation <hi>of our ſayd</hi> Prince <hi>of</hi> Wales <hi>be heere recorded by vs, for a memoriall to all ſucceeding times: and ſo againe we ſay; God ſaue and bleſſe Prince</hi> Charles <hi>our ſaid</hi> Prince <hi>of</hi> Wales, <hi>and his royall Poſterity for euer.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p rend="small">Theſe were the words of that reuerend Iudge, there wanteth nothing ſaue that Grace and Zeale wherewith he pronounced them.</p>
            <p>Whereunto all the people with a loud voyce prayed and cryed, <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thereupon all the Muſick played, Drums were ſtrucke, Flutes whiſtled, Trumpets ſounded, people ſhowted, and another piercing and thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Volley of ſhot was let flie, the eccho and report whereof reſounded admirably, to the great ſolace and comfort of all preſent.</p>
            <p>And then being full one of the clocke in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noone, the ſaid <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and Counſell, with the Knights, Eſquiers, and beſt ſort of Gentlemen returned into the Caſtle to dinner (where was a great Feaſt prouided, with excellent muſicke) the Bailiffes alſo with their Brethren and Burgeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes went downe to the Towne, to ſpend the reſt of the day in all joyfull and iouiall manner, hauing
<pb facs="tcp:15431:13"/>all of them, before their departure thence, in the preſence, and by the appointment of <hi>Raph Manſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> Eſquier, chiefe Steward to the Kings Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold there, drunke plentifully of wine, to the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie health and proſperitie, of our ſaid gracious Prince of <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dinner being ſcarſe ended in the Caſtle, the aforeſaide Bailiffes in like pompe, beeing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine accompanied with the whole Quire of the Church, and the Penon-bearers with their Bane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rols of Armes in their hands, and their Muſicke playing before them, came vp in great ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie into the Caſtle, where Maiſter <hi>Iuſtice</hi> ioyfully receiuing them, brought them ſtraight into the Chappell, there to offer their Euening Sacrifice, where much reioycing was without doores, and excellent Muſicke of Voyces, in ſinging many Pſalmes and new Anthemes within the ſaide Chappell.</p>
            <p>VVhich being finiſhed, the aforeſaid Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers very humbly proſtrating themſelues with low obeiſance, deliuered vp their ſayd ſeuerall Banerolls into the hands of the ſaid <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> who willed <hi>Richard Adams</hi> Gentleman, being skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in <hi>Heraldrie</hi> there preſent, to ſee them or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly placed in the ſaid Chappel, where they now remaine as remarkeable Trophies of that Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</p>
            <p>And after Prayers ended, the Bailiffes with their company humbly taking their leaue of the
<pb facs="tcp:15431:13"/>Counſell, Maiſter <hi>Iuſtice</hi> required them ſtill to continue their Ringing, as well for the full ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnizing of the ſaid day of our <hi>Prince</hi> his ſayd <hi>Creation,</hi> as alſo to expreſſe their ioy and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing vnto Almightie God for our ſaid dread Soueraignes moſt admirable Deliuerance, with the royall Queene, illuſtrious Prince, all the Lords Spirituall and Temporall, and Commons of this Realme aſſembled together in Parliament from the Papiſts treaſonable and horrible conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie, and vnmatchable intended Practiſe of the Gunne-powder treaſon, in the yeare of our Lord God, one thouſand ſixe hundred and fiue, and to bee in a readineſſe with the ſayd <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and Counſell the next morning, to praiſe God for the ſame.</p>
            <p>VVhich accordingly was performed the next day, and a very learned Sermon preached by Maiſter <hi>Thomas Kaye,</hi> the Kings Chaplaine, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the Lord Preſident and Counſell there, vpon the twelue and thirteene Verſes of the 116. Pſalme.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>What ſhall I render vnto the Lord for all his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites towards me?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I will take the cup of Saluation, and call vpon the name of the Lord.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Which Sermon being ended, euery man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to their home, the Muſicke, Ringing, and Bonefires continuing to the great comfort of all
<pb facs="tcp:15431:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>his Maieſties ſaid louing and faithfull Subiects all the ſaid day.</p>
            <p>This Solemnization the ſaid <hi>Iuſtice</hi> was care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to obſerue, for the <hi>Glorie</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Honour</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Wales;</hi> as well to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and expreſſe his Duetie and Seruice, as alſo the loyaltie and heartie ioy of all his Maieſties louing Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects then aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15431:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
